Guide to the Joe Sitter Collection of Gaylord Schanilec, 1980-2015 RL.11225
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Joe Sitter collection of Gaylord Schanilec
1980-2015 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sitter, Joe
RL.11225
5.0 Linear Feet
Joe Sitter is a collector and friend of Gaylord Schanilec. Gaylord Schanilec is a notable American wood engraver, printer, designer and illustrator. He is the proprietor of the press Midnight Paper Sales, located in Stockholm, Wisconsin. Sitter's collection includes original wood engravings, publications, clippings, printer's waste, correspondence, and other materials documenting the artwork and career of Gaylord Schanilec.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into three series: Artwork, Publications Files, and Subject Files.
Biographical / Historical
Gaylord Schanilec is a notable American wood engraver, printer, designer and illustrator. He is the proprietor of the press Midnight Paper Sales, located in Stockholm, Wisconsin.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Joe Sitter Collection of Gaylord Schanilec was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift and purchase from Joe Sitter in 2016.
Related Materials
See also the Joe Sitter Collection of Fine Printing. There are also a number of monographs removed from this collection to be cataloged as individual items in the Rubenstein Library.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of Joe Sitter's files and acquired artwork documenting the career of Gaylord Schanilec, including examples of Schanilec's wood engravings; fine printing prospectuses and keepsakes featuring Schanilec's work; Schanilec illustrations from publications by Midnight Paper Sales and the Gregynog Press; printer's waste and other printing scraps; clippings and articles documenting Schanilec's career, public appearances, and publications; correspondence between Sitter and Schanilec; and some photographs of Schanilec.
Wood-engraving -- 20th century; Artists -- United States; Publishers and publishing -- United States; Fine books; Letterpress printing; Sitter, Joe; Schanilec, Gaylord; Midnight Paper Sales Press
- Artwork, 1981-2013 and undated
  - Pelecanus erythrorhynchos, 2010 (Box 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Pelecanus erythrorhynchos. Color woodcut. Number 135/250. Signed, dated 2010. Dimensions: 10.5 x 17", framed 21 x 27"
  - Cherry: End Grain, 2007 (Box 4)
    Cherry: End Grain. Color woodcut. Number 5/7. Signed, dated 2007. Dimensions 5.5 x 10". Frame created from the cherry featured in the woodcut: 15 x 20".
  - Walnut: End Grain, 2007 (Box 5)
    Walnut: End Grain. Color woodcut. Number 3/4. Signed, dated 2007. Dimensions: 6 x 10". Frame created out of walnut featured in the woodcut: 15 x 19.5".
  - Minnehaha, undated (Box 6)
    Minnehaha. Color woodcut. Numbered 13/50. Signed, undated. Dimensions: 5.5 x 10".
  - [Times Square], undated (Box 6)
    [Times Square]. Color woodcut. Number 166/180. Signed, undated. Dimension: 5.5 x 9.5".
  - Fresh Carp, 1981 (Box 6)
    Fresh Carp. Color woodcut. Number 108/110. Signed, dated 1981. Dimensions: 10.25 x 18.5".
  - [Trees and hill], undated (Box 6)
    [Trees and hill]. Color woodcut. Number 45/100. Signed, undated. Paper has press seal: The Gregynog Press. Dimensions: 9.75 x 15".
  - Hard Maple, undated (Box 6)
    Hard Maple. Color woodcut. Number 33/80. Signed, undated. Dimensions: 14.25 x 25.5".
  - [Fish], printer's waste, with note to Joe Sitter ("Hi Uncle Joe!"), undated (Box 6)
  - Pool Four of the Mississippi River, 2013 (Oversize-folder 1)
    Pool Four of the Mississippi River. Map and color woodcut. Signed, dated 2013. Dimensions: 32 x 24.5".
  - Lexington Ave., undated (Box 1)
    Color woodcut. Number 83/100. Signed, undated. 6.75 x 11.5".
  - A Very Small Composing Table, undated (Box 1)
    Color woodcut. Numbered 49/49. Signed, undated. 6 x 8.25".
  - Rufas, undated (Box 1)
    Color woodcut. Numbered 17/27. Signed, undated. 6 x 5".
  - Rulon's Moon, 2012 (Box 1)
    Woodcut. Numbered 107/120. Signed, dated 2012.
- Gaylord Schanilec Subject Files, 1980s-2015
  Joe Sitter's collection of correspondence, articles, notes, and other assorted materials related to Schanilec's work and career.
  - Correspondence between Joe Sitter and Gaylord Schanilec, 2000s (Box 2)
    Includes handwritten notes and printed emails, as well as occasional printer's waste and other woodcuts created by Schanilec and mailed or collected by Sitter.
  - Minnesota Center for Book Arts exhibit: From Start to Here, 2010 (Box 2)
  - Gaylord Schanilec publicity and ephemera, 1980s-2000s (Box 2)
    Appearances, scraps, and other materials relating to Schanilec's publications and art shows.
  - Miscellaneous publications and prospectuses (Box 2)
    Assorted publications and prospectuses for smaller or minor works created by Schanilec
  - Bibliographica, 2005-2015 (Box 2)
    Notes and materials collected by Sitter as he prepared a bibliography of Schanilec's career.
  - Matrix offprints, 1980s-2000s (Box 2)
    Articles by and about Schanilec published in Matrix, the fine printing publication.
  - Articles about Schanilec, 1980s-2015 (Box 2)
  - Printing History, issue number 11, Jan. 2012 (Box 2)
  - Photographs/images of Schanilec, 1980s-2000s (Box 2)
  - The Private Library, vol. 41, 2011 (Box 2)
- Publication Files, 1980s-2015
  Arrangement
  Foldered alphabetically by title. Joe Sitter's original folders tended to include handwritten notes about each folder's content. These have been photocopied when necessary and included in the front of the folder.
  - The Bicycle Diaries, 2011 (Box 1)
    Prospectuses
  - Euphemisms from a Catholic Childhood, 1980 (Box 1)
    Numbered 3/30. From Midnight Paper Sales Press.
  - High Bridge, 1987-2015 (Box 1)
    Includes prospectus.
  - Lac des Pleurs, 2015 and undated (Box 1)
    Includes seashell.
  - Mayflies of the Driftless Region, 2012 and undated (Box 1)
    Includes sample prints, research, notes, prospectus.
  - New York Revisited, 2002 (Box 1)
    Printed for the Grolier Club. Includes prospectus.
  - Sylvæ, 2007 and undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Includes articles, photographs, wood sample, a wood block "White Oak" (Number 030), other materials and publicity re: Sylvæ
  - Thomas McGrath publications, 1991-1997 and undated (Box 1)
    Includes "On Returning," prospectuses, other materials re: McGrath's poetry.
  - Waterfalls of the Mississippi, 2007 and undated (Box 1)
    Articles, research, publicity, etc.
  - Wrenching Times, 1991 (Box 1)
    Includes prospectus and keepsake.